these days everything is unlimited
unlimited food at a buffet unlimited
data on your phone unlimited data for
even your Wi-Fi and the same trend has
been picked by the health insurance
companies and they're calling it
unlimited summon Shard so to debunk all
the myth that is around unlimited summon
sh today I have with me rashab Kash a
new face here at the ditto Studio who
will help us answer all the questions
that you have and I myself have about
unlimited sum insur in health insurance
first of all welcome rashab pleasure to
be here SE thank you for having me again
so let's start right away is Su insur
which is unlimited sum insur a marketing
gimmick that's coming into the health
insurance industry uh let's start from
there that's that's the question that's
right on top of my head well uh to
answer that I would say it's yes and no
yes it's a marketing uh you know stunt
to attract more individuals to buy their
plans and no because it is also a
necessity and a need for a lot of people
who are looking at you know ensuring
that they have an adequate uh insurance
coverage on their plans to ensure that
there aren't many out of pocket expenses
understood but uh let me point out to
one data U actually a couple of data
points an average surgery say for a
cataract or cost of cancer treatment
usually doesn't go go anywhere above say
5 10 15 lakhs so why is this 1 CR or
unlimited coverage even coming into the
picture well it's all about requirement
I would say right so even though the
high value of claims May range between
15 to 20 lakhs a lot of claims at least
a good chunk of them right so the
possibility as well as the probability
of even costing 15 to 20 lakhs you know
would be very less so if you look at the
ird's um you know annual reports right
so the Insurance uh Regulators put out
you know annual report on a year on-ear
basis so you will see uh proper
statistical points as to what are the
claim amounts how much you know certain
you know treatments cost and even on a
geographical level uh as well uh right
so I would say if you look at the recent
annual report honestly it was quite
surprising because it did not cost more
than 37,000 okay yeah but when we are
talking about high value claims which
can range from anywhere between 15 to 20
lakhs and in the off chance it may even
uh cost a lot more as well ranging from
even 25 lakhs up to 30 lakhs if you're
talking about transplants in certain you
know hospitals a quick question here why
did companies go ahead and start
unlimited coverage and what were the
points that they considered well it all
falls down to actu real science
basically where uh the insurers see what
exactly are the probabilities of someone
actually you know making a claim for
certain you know amounts uh they look at
the average of all the claims uh that
that were made in the past and what the
probabilities of those claims coming up
again and what what are those high value
claims and what are those low value
claims so they look at the uh you know
irda report as well as they look at the
current trends and take all these
insights and they build these policies
where they you know offer unlimited
coverage some policies even uh right so
just to name a few would be AO uh you
know Platinum
which offers unlimited coverage and
followed by even companies like Star
health insurance which has a policy by
the name of Superstar and not to mention
the fact lastly with you know the icsa
Lombards eleate policy right you know uh
interestingly we made a video on all
these topics and one thing that stood
out was uh we saw this trend right uh
I'm not sure I think it was AO first
coming in with the unlimited plan and uh
when we saw that they were offering a
plan worth uh you know over over a CR or
even unlimited for a good reasonable
price uh that's when we saw companies
like even Lombard you know coming in to
the mix and giving uh the Elevate plan
and then the most recent entr into it is
a superstar policy kind of a savior of
star you know now what I see is a trend
that is coming in
in order to save uh the customers you
know from high prices is is that
understanding right or do you think that
this is in order to retain the customers
uh you know for them to switch over to a
higher summon short like what's your
take on this well a lot of people have
concerns about the adequacy of their
health insurance coverage do you get
those questions a lot is you know do
people ask you is this enough is this is
this enough yeah of course because a lot
of times when we speak to you know some
of our customers uh one of the
frequently asked questions is what would
be the summer short that you would
recommend all right so of course so
there uh is that's when we bring out
topics such as know considering the uh
Trends towards the medical cost medical
inflation and all these know important
macroeconomic points towards know the
healthcare we ideally recommend going
for some around 10 to even maybe like 20
lakhs to cover at least a good chunk of
the major medical costs which are of
course the the high value claims right
right now as a consumer of not just
health insurance if I have something in
abundance RAB I would go ahead and use
it to the max that's something that
humans are you know coded to do indeed
uh do you see that happening with people
over utilizing their insurance in a way
that that because they have unlimited
some insured now do you think frequent
hospitalization would be more do you
think there would be overutilization of
your medical cover so how do you see
this uh panning out even though
unlimited coverage often uh provide
certain benefits such as comprehensive
coverage Financial Security as well as
the most important thing an insurance
should provide which is a piece of mind
one thing that people need to understand
is the risks that are associated with
these kind of policies now at the end of
the day it can only be truly unlimited
when the risk pool for the insurance
companies um and the users who bought
those plants are so huge that the
insurance companies have no issues
whatsoever providing and giving out
those kind of benefits because the
sustainability aspect of those companies
is where it all falls down to because at
the end of the day if the insurance
companies cannot pay for those kind of
coverage and those kind of benefits that
they are promising so when that day
eventually arrives it'll be like they
are over promising at the beginning but
they end up underd delivering on those
promises which should never be the case
with any insurers I think that is what
segments a good insurer from a bad one a
bad one right now you brought up the
topic about the three insurers currently
in the Market at least in our uh
Spotlight uh aquip Platinum Superstar
and then IC eluate uh let's hear about
them let's hear about their unlimited
plans and what is it that they're
offering and if you have gotten the
chance to get a hold of their premiums
how much do they cost speaking on
premiums uh for an average 30-year-old
individual it may cost anywhere between
24 to
25,000 but when we talk about someone
who is of a much older age say a senior
citizens the premiums can eventually end
up going above know 70,000 to 1 lakh for
an individual person and if you're
talking about a floater plan which
involves know two adults especially
senior citizen parents it can hover
between 1.5 to 1.6 lakhs perom for an
unlimited coverage right uh another
question as probably a policy holder or
a potential policy holder is when I'm
presented with two plans say one average
plan which is promising me higher
actually in fact unlimited some insured
and one which is offering me a decent Su
insured but is a very good insurer as a
consumer what do I need to consider do I
go in with the unlimited insurer uh
sorry the unlimited Su insured with an
average insurer or a decent Su insured
with a very good insurer well I would
say it's a decent coverage with an uh
you know a good company or a great
company for that matter because you do
always have different sumers shur
options
um you know with those kind of insurers
so you have something as basic as a five
L coverage and uh you have something as
large as you know one or two crores
worth of coverage amount of course that
would not be necessary speaking on the
lines of um decent companies offering
unlimited coverages consumers can can be
in the receiving end of significant
price hikes if the insurance companies
receive large amount of claims so the
Premium Adjustments can be at a
significantly larger uh percentage not
even just on a year- on-ear basis uh
from know the medical inflation but also
even because of uh know their age as
well so on an average if insurers uh
change their premium say about every 2
years to every four years by about 10 to
15% uh average companies that provide
the unlimited uh restoration can end up
doing this on an annual basis going
about close to you know 20% I'm not
saying that this has happened I'm saying
that it may happen because you can never
predict what the future actually holds
and if the insurer requires such huge
amounts of premiums they will definitely
end up doing so and not only that it's
also from the plans being continued in
the market itself because the insurer
can end up reassessing their entire
model about providing such policies and
they can even uh shelf that product
completely uh so that you know no new
user or new consumer can actually go for
that plan great so if you had one final
takeaway for someone in the audience
who's out there uh when venturing into
buying an unlimited summon sh short plan
uh what would be your two cents on that
well firstly reach out to ditto speak to
our folks where you have seasoned
advisers who will always be there to
assist you with your proper plans
compared health insurance tell you the
nuances and the pros and cons of uh the
policies with unlimited coverage and the
policies um you know with great
companies are don't offer unlimited
coverages so that would always be the
first option and you can do as much
research as you want uh know from your
end find uh the policies that are best
suited for your uh know financial needs
and from your affordability as well
great that was sweet and short thank you
so much rashab uh this has really
cleared the air around uh unlimited some
insur so folks there you have it this
brings us to the end of the video well
if you like the video then drop a like
And subscribe for more content on
insurance I will see you in the next one
happy insurance hunting